<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-19T10:16:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FitHome</title><subtitle>Trim the Fat from your Electricity Bills.</subtitle><author><name>HappyDay</name></author><entry><title type="html">Easy to make a web site</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/04/18/In-Process.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Easy to make a web site" /><published>2019-04-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/18/In-Process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/04/18/In-Process.html">&lt;p&gt;I used GitHub pages to create the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitknitting.github.io/FitHome_web/&quot;&gt;FitHome web site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
GitHub has a nifty way to build a website that uses Jekyll. I’m new to Jekyll.  So far there is alot to like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can write pages in markdown.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is heavily template based - this reminds me alot like Flask.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A web site can start off with a basic template.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A local web site can run that automagically updates when changes are made to the file (like Flask).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I have already installed a local copy of Jekyll.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;steps&quot;&gt;Steps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to start with &lt;a href=&quot;https://startbootstrap.com/themes/clean-blog-jekyll/&quot;&gt;the clean blog template from Start Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;.  The tree and template structure is already Jekyll aware.  It uses Bootstrap to make styling the site easier.  It has a look I like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copied to my local repo directory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changed the base URL to “/”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Made sure it worked on Localhost:4000.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deleted the original .git directory (I found deleting Start Bootstrap’s repo the easiest way to link to my remote repo)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Created a git repository: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git init&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Created a gh_pages branch.  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git checkout -b gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;Note: The github pages doc says the website can be created under master.  I had a heckuva time with this so I fell back to blindly following steps from YouTube videos, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fqFjuX4VZmU&quot;&gt;like this one, Hosting on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push local git to gitHub ```&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git add .&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modify baseurl in _config.yml to be name of GitHub repo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Created a new repository - &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;FitHome_web&lt;/a&gt; without a Readme.md.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went into Settings/Branches and set &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; as the default branch.  I did this to make sure I always went to this branch.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push git adds to the gitHub repo &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git push origin gh-pages&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turn on pages in Settings if not already on.  Make sure to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>HappyDay</name></author><summary type="html">I used GitHub pages to create the FitHome web site. GitHub has a nifty way to build a website that uses Jekyll. I’m new to Jekyll. So far there is alot to like: I can write pages in markdown. It is heavily template based - this reminds me alot like Flask. A web site can start off with a basic template. A local web site can run that automagically updates when changes are made to the file (like Flask). Note: I have already installed a local copy of Jekyll. Steps I decided to start with the clean blog template from Start Bootstrap. The tree and template structure is already Jekyll aware. It uses Bootstrap to make styling the site easier. It has a look I like. Copied to my local repo directory. Changed the base URL to “/”. Made sure it worked on Localhost:4000. Deleted the original .git directory (I found deleting Start Bootstrap’s repo the easiest way to link to my remote repo) Created a git repository: git init Created a gh_pages branch. git checkout -b gh-pages Note: The github pages doc says the website can be created under master. I had a heckuva time with this so I fell back to blindly following steps from YouTube videos, like this one, Hosting on GitHub. Push local git to gitHub ``` git add . Modify baseurl in _config.yml to be name of GitHub repo. Created a new repository - FitHome_web without a Readme.md. Went into Settings/Branches and set gh-pages as the default branch. I did this to make sure I always went to this branch. Push git adds to the gitHub repo git push origin gh-pages. Turn on pages in Settings if not already on. Make sure to use gh-pages branch.</summary></entry></feed>